# **Howard Kier**

(847) 910-9875 ♦ https://howardkier.com ♦ howard@mmpix.com ♦ linkedin.com/in/hkier

#### **WEB DEVELOPER**

Returning to my first love, coding, I have enhanced my skills by constantly learning new technologies. A Software Engineer with a BS and MS from Syracuse University and an MBA from Southern Methodist University I bring unique perspectives and experiences to effectively solve today's problems.

# **NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS**

- Coded and tested various components for decarbonizemystate.com.
- Wrote "Cyber Scams and You", volumes 1 and 2 currently in the publication stage.
- Led assessment projects for companies with 500-1000 employees resulting in increased business and income for EDS.
- Proactively negotiated among multiple stakeholders with conflicting priorities and requirements to work toward a common and satisfying solution.
- Assessed financial performance of a small business, creating budgets, balance sheets, cash flows, and P&L statements twice a year.
- Efficiently streamlined client business operations and reduced business costs by analyzing present and future business needs, assessing systems, and presenting specific recommendations to improve business processes and supporting systems.

#### **CURRENT PROJECTS**

- Creating a patient medicine management system to remind patients to take their medications, call the pharmacy for refills and even schedule doctors' appointments when required.
- Designing and implementing a web application for Boy Scout Troop 497 to take food orders, determine customers' final price, aggregate orders and display reports to eliminate paper orders, reduce cost and minimize errors.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE and ACCOMPLISHMENTS

# FREELANCE WEB DEVELOPER, Schaumburg, IL. Consultant/Web Developer

2018-2023

Consultant/Web Developer

Partnered with clients to determine project requirements and delivered high-quality results on-time and within budget.

- Updated and migrated 2 websites for the Friends of Wilderness Road from an old HTML based website to a content
  management system (WIX) which will allows the client to regularly update website content themselves rather than a
  developer.
- Developed stevenrosenblum.com to support a local candidate's campaign for local Board of Education.
- Closed multiple change requests for Chicagodoulaproject.com as part of Chi Hack Night development team by creating components to meet project requirements and deadlines.

# HARDESTY, HACKETT and PARTNERS, Atlanta, GA./LEGACY ANALYTICS, Rolling Meadows, IL. 2013 – 2017 Management Consultant

Analyzed current business status (financials, operations, personnel and systems) to identify problems, presented improvement recommendations and implemented the changes for companies in the manufacturing, restaurant, retail, logistics and trucking industries.

- Accurately analyzed work processes, systems, organizational function and structures using interviews, observation, data and statistical analysis studies to determine where and how to generate measurable benefits resulting in an average of \$125K savings per year per client.
- Organized employees into logical departments to improve communication, reduce errors and minimize organizational dysfunction.
- Prepared written and oral feedback, presentation materials, critiques, systems documentation, process descriptions, proposals, standard operating procedures, evaluations, data summaries and reports.
- Determined Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) and trained client executives in the effective use of management systems, tools, and techniques to better monitor company status.

# MAGICAL MOMENTS PHOTOGRAPHY, Schaumburg, IL.

2002 - 2013

On-location photography studio specializing in weddings, special occasions, and corporate events.

#### **Business Owner and Operations Director**

Operated and managed on-location photography business. Planned and implemented marketing, financials, and business operations. Directly managed staff of 5, including employees and contractors responsible for sales and photography.

- Evaluated and selected vendors and project partners based on cost, services, and client satisfaction.
- Reviewed and updated business plans twice a year.

- Performed competitor and market analysis on products, services, and pricing twice a year.to predict product sales, design product offerings and establish pricing.
- Investigated impact of current and predicted future economies and incorporated this information into the business plan.
- Assessed financial performance of business, creating budget, balance sheets, cash flows, and P&L statements twice a year.
- Worked closely with clients to clarify requirements, expectations, and offer solutions.
- Managed accounts payable and receivable ensuring consistent cash flow in all seasons by managing client payment schedules.
- Collaborated with publisher, venue, florist, planner, and baker to create party-scape for Wedding Guide Chicago magazine.
- Collaborated with studio to execute on site printing in response to unique client request.

#### EDS CORPORATION, Chicago, IL.

1997 - 2002

### **Advanced Systems Engineer, Production Support Department**

Applied SDLC processes to the development of new and existing programs to meet user requirements, resulting in reduced costs, and resolved problems for users and clients.

### **Payroll Processing Conversion Project**

- Reduced payroll costs by converting system to an updated payroll processing system.
- Managed project from inception through implementation.
- Managed team including EDS staff, contractors, vendors, and client.

#### **Positive Pay System Project**

- Saved EDS Client \$300,000+ by developing and implementing a positive pay system solution to prevent acceptance of fraudulent checks.
- Facilitated efforts among two banks, the EDS client, and the EDS IT department.

#### **Business Systems Assessment Projects**

- Led three and actively consulted on 10 assessment projects for companies with 500-1000 employees. Resulted in increased business and income for EDS.
- Streamlined client business operations and reduced business costs by analyzing present and future business needs, assessing systems, and presenting specific recommendations to improve business processes and supporting systems.

# Advanced Business Analyst, Costing, Pricing and Billing Department

Reengineered manual processes to increase efficiency. Audited invoices. Analyzed data.

- Reduced time to audit invoices by 90% by designing and implementing an automated invoice audit system.
- Decreased the time required to develop rates by delivering process improvements.
- Assured profitability by developing financial cost models for the evaluation of new and existing communication products and services. Collaborated with teams of up to 12 people.
- Certified competitive pricing for new and existing data communication network products by performing competitive analysis and investigating costs.

# **EDUCATION and TRAINING**

MBA, Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Tx., Beta Gamma Sigma honor society member

MS, Computer Engineering, Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY.

BS, Computer Engineering, Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY.

Approved Business Instructor, Professional Photographers of America, Atlanta, GA.

#### TECHNICAL/COMPUTER SKILLS

- Mainframe: IBM/360 Rexx, APL, MVS, JCL and SQL
- Midrange: RPG IV, CL, J.D. Edwards Enterprise Software: A/P, A/R, Financial, Inventory, and Payroll, SQL
- Web Technologies: Express, JavaScript, Node, React, Redux, Sequalize, HTML, Postgres/MySQL, CSS, jQuery, Socket.io, Webpack, and Github
- Other Skills: MS Office, including Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, SDLC, System Conversion Strategies, Project Management and Planning, Financial Analysis, Process Improvement and Testing Processes

### **VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES**

BOY SCOUTS/CUB SCOUTS, Schaumburg, IL. CHIHACK NIGHT, Chicago, IL. VERY INTERESTED PARENTS, Schaumburg, IL. SAXON BAND BOOSTERS, Schaumburg, IL.

2009 – Current 2018-Current 2014-Current 2017-2021